What is an operating system? It's a good question. We've been talking a lot about operating systems
We never really actually defined what one is and you might not have actually given a much thought to what an operating system is
Even though you kind of know what one is you have one on your phone your computer your game console
An operating system or an OS is a collection of programs that manages the internal workings of the computer
So when a program wants to write data of then retrieve it later
The OS ensures that the application is able to do so as quickly easily and safely as possible
An operating system has a number of management functions process management security management file management
communications management resource management and memory management
The way all these work together is really what makes up the heart of the OS
Typically applications running on an operating system interface with the operating system through a simplified series of interfaces called
API's or
Application programming interfaces
Let's get into one of those functions process management typically a process can be in one of five states
New ready running waiting and terminated in the new state the process is in the stage of being created
It's being built in the ready state the process is ready. It's waiting for pickup
But the CPU is busy doing something else in the running state the CPU has grabbed that process
It's picked it up and it's actively working with it
Okay, now the waiting state. This is where it gets a little bit interesting a process typically doesn't just start and end
All by itself it might need to read some data prompt the user for some input
Or it might have to kick off a couple sub processes and while it's doing that while it's waiting for them to fit
Finish the process can be put into a wait state and when it's in a wait state
It's it's waiting and finally when the process is accomplished its task and there's nothing else for it to do
It goes into the terminated state
So you can see the general flow of things here
It starts out new and then it goes into ready and then it goes into running from there
It either goes into the terminated state which says it's done for one reason or another
It either did everything it needed to do or something else happened or it goes back to ready
There are two ways it can go back to ready the first is in the case of a wait
Where it's waiting for more data user input or for another process to finish or if the CPU is like hey
I know you're really busy and you're trying to do your stuff
I've got a bunch of other programs try to do something too
So I'll be right back and that's called an interrupt and interrupt is just that it kind of it interrupts the process
And says sit right here be patient go into a ready state and I'll come back and get you and finish you when I have time to do that
That's the only way that a computer can work on multiple programs at the same time now a process can go back and forth between
Running and ready a whole bunch of times before it completes
That's a good thing because if programs could only run in a straight line from ready to finished
We wouldn't be able to run more than one program at a time on a computer
Then there's security management
Obviously security very very important on a mainframe because we're dealing with the world's most important financial data
Health records personal records so security very important. We're going to talk more about that later
Up next file management on the Z we try to offload as much of the work away from the application to the OS as possible
So rather than making the application keep track of where everything was stored and where to get later
We let the file management handle that
Communications management takes care of all the network communications very very important and then there's the resource management
This makes sure that all of the programs running on the system played nicely with one another
It looks at everything competing for the same resources like
CPU memory network disk and it makes sure everyone kind of gets a fair spot at those resources
resource management is the cornerstone of modern computing and
Lastly, there's memory management. We're going to get into this in much greater detail later on
But suffice to say on the mainframe
We want our applications to run as quickly and efficiently as possible and one way of doing that is by abstracting all the
Complexities of memory management away from the developer and their applications and handling them in the memory management function and there you have it
That's your six management functions of an operating system now
Some of them might have seen obvious while others might not seem all that vital
But I tell you what you take away any one of them and you'd have a really hard time getting anything done on a modern operating system